Speaker 1: Bloomberg's in-house economists just dropped a savage new report that traded their standard China cheerleading for some doom,
Speaker 1: contending that China, quote, may never overtake the U.S. economy.
Speaker 1: Meanwhile, the U.S. Commerce Secretary is now warning China has become, quote,
Speaker 1: uninvestable for foreign companies who had long seen it as a free market paradise.
Speaker 1: So this is a big deal because for 35 years now, it has been an article of faith that China was going to inherit the earth.
Speaker 1: China's rise was inevitable, and we were all living on borrowed time.
Speaker 1: Now, don't get me wrong, we are living on borrowed time.
Speaker 1: The disastrous policies made since the 2008 crisis, really since Richard Nixon,
Speaker 1: are putting us on an unsustainable path to permanent stagflation,
Speaker 1: flattening our growth prospects until we finally hit that financial singularity that is too big to bail out.
Speaker 1: The problem is China is headed to the same place, maybe even faster.
Speaker 1: I've done a couple of recent videos on China's rapid collapse.
Speaker 1: In short, Xi channeled trillions to politically favored industries at the expense of the dynamic bits of the economy,
Speaker 1: leading to both manufacturing and property now in free fall.
Speaker 1: Those two sectors make up half of China's economy, much more than the U.S.,
Speaker 1: so that's dragging the entire country down,
Speaker 1: leading to rising joblessness, especially among the young who always get fired first.
Speaker 1: And, as in this country, financial and bank failures spreading like wildfire.
Speaker 1: Bigger and bigger they march towards that moment, Beijing can't bail them all out.
Speaker 1: Now, Bloomberg takes this clown show and runs with it, citing deep-seated structural problems,
Speaker 1: predicting a slower China for decades to come.
Speaker 1: Specifically, they now think China could momentarily pip the U.S. sometime in the 2040s,
Speaker 1: but then immediately fall behind again as China's population shrivels,
Speaker 1: thanks to their idiotic one-child policy that appears to have become a social norm.
Speaker 1: So, seven years after one-child ended, China's currently sporting 1.09 births per woman.
Speaker 1: For a sense, if that continued for a generation, or for three generations, a century,
Speaker 1: China's population would drop eight-fold, to about half what it is in the U.S.
Speaker 1: Now, keep in mind, that doesn't mean China's poor, it simply means they're number two,
Speaker 1: maybe number three if India keeps plugging away,
Speaker 1: which doesn't really matter day-to-day, it's more of a prestige and power thing,
Speaker 1: but it is a big change from the doomsday predictions of the past decades,
Speaker 1: and it suggests that China may already be past its peak of power.
Speaker 1: So, what's next?
Speaker 1: I think Bloomberg's being short-sighted, Xi is not immortal,
Speaker 1: and China has a lot more free-market bureaucrats than the U.S., or, God forbid, Europe.
Speaker 1: Yes, China's in for some lean days, and those would hit a lot of poor countries like Africa,
Speaker 1: who depend on exports to China.
Speaker 1: But Xi himself has got a lot of opposition inside the Chinese government,
Speaker 1: despite building a personal police state, so he could retire surprisingly soon.
Speaker 1: Moreover, the victory laps are delusional, because unless the West reverses our rapid plunge into socialism,
Speaker 1: the Asian policy mix will win, whether or not China's on board.
Speaker 1: So, what we see in Korea, Singapore, or Taiwan, where the economy is nurtured because it is the social safety net,
Speaker 1: because prosperity leads to the rest, rather than today's West,
Speaker 1: which crushes the real economy to buy votes or to fund activists who prefer to burn things instead.
Speaker 1: Okay, we'll be watching.
Speaker 1: See you next time.